This entire house was destroyed in one night.
यह पूरा घर एक रात में तबाह हो गया। ये
Look at this.  These shells fell in your house.  It
देखिए। ये गोले आपके घर में गिरे। यहां से
is attached here.  Here, the walls, the
लगा है। यहां पर निकला है दीवारों का,
TV, everything is broken.
टीवी का यानी कि पूरी चीजें टूट गई है।
My mother's face was completely cut.
फेस पूरा कट चुका था मेरी मम्मा का। उनकी
Because of him my mother died.  These are the
वजह से मेरी मम्मा की डेथ हो गई। ये है वो
shells that fell not just on walls but right in the
शेल्स गोले जो सिर्फ दीवारों पर नहीं
middle of people's lives.  This
लोगों के जीवन के बीचों-बीच गिरे। यह वाला
shell has fallen.  Here too.  They can see that the
शेल गिरा है। इधर भी। वो देख सकते हैं
tree has been cut.  The
पेड़ कटा हुआ है। जब जंग के गोले बेकसूरों
entire city becomes a ghost town as war shells fall on the heads of innocent people.
के सर पर गिरते हैं तो पूरा शहर एक गोस्ट
Like Uri is just 10 km from the border.
टाउन बन जाता है। जैसे उरी सीमा से बस 10
Shells fell here far away for a week.
कि.मी. दूर यहां एक हफ्ते तक गोले गिरे।
You will remember that time differently.  You will
आप उस टाइम अलग को याद करोगे। बाकी कुछ
not see anything else.  You will say that an idol is hovering over your head.
नहीं देखोगे। बोलोगे आपके सर पे मूर्त
We made this video
मंडरा रही है। ये वीडियो हमने बनाई हमारे
with the help of our local Kashmiri followers who visited this house.
लोकल कश्मीरी फॉलोअर्स की मदद से जो इस घर
When the whole family of this house
में गए। इस घर की पूरी फैमिली जब गाड़ी
ran away in fear in the car, it brought back only painful memories.  The
में डर के भागी तो वापस बस दर्दनाक यादें
lights of our car came on and the entire
लेकर आई। हमारे गाड़ी के लाइट जली और पूरी
car was in the air.  Because of the wind we went all up
गाड़ी हवा में थी। हवा की वजह से हम पूरे
and down.  The face was completely cut.
ऊपर अप और डाउन हुए। फेस पूरा कट चुका था।
My mother's blood had
मेरी मम्मा का उनका जो ब्लड था वो इतना
become so warm.  It was coming out from his entire mouth.
वार्म हो चुका था। वो पूरे पूरे मुंह से
Because of him my mother
निकल रहा था। उनकी वजह से मेरी मम्मा की
died.
डेथ हो गई।
When there is a war between two countries, another
जब जंग दो देशों के बीच चलती है तो एक और
war is to save everyday life.   The
जंग रोजमर्रा की जिंदगी बचाने की होती है।
battle to save children, farming, and earnings.  Only Allah used to hear our voices
जंग। हमारी आवाजें सिर्फ अल्लाह सुनता था
and no one else, no one else.   It
और कोई नहीं सुनता था बस और कोई नहीं।
came from here, it came from here.  And
यहां से ये निकला यहां से आया है। और ये
look, it has fallen here.  Nobody
ये देखो यहां पर गिरा है। हमें किसी ने
threw us out.  We ran away ourselves.  We ran away ourselves.  There
नहीं निकाला। हम खुद भाग गए। हम खुद भाग
is a veranda.  Veranda veranda that's where we
गए। वरांडा है। वरांडा वरांडा वहीं पर हम
hid.  My knees were bruised.  The
छुपे थे। हमारे जो घुटने हैं ना वो छिल गए
children, the children, had fallen unconscious.
थे। बच्चों बच्चे बच्चे बेहोश हो गए थे।
Our mother will not be able to come back.  She was
हमारी मम्मा तो वापस नहीं आ पाएगी। वो तो
martyred for the country.  We are happy with that.
देश के लिए शहीद हुई। उस बात से हम खुश
But we are thinking about it.  We appeal
हैं। पर हम ये सोच रहे हैं। हम ये अपील
to the government that if we have to fight a war then we have to do anything.
करते गवर्नमेंट से अगर जंग भी करना है कुछ
First keep the people safe.
भी करना है। पहले पीपल्स को सेफ तो करो।
If you were a banker, you would have been safe.  There is
अगर बैंकर होते, सेफ होते। हमें यहां
no need for us to run away here.  We are
भागने की कोई जरूरत नहीं होती। हम कहीं
not going anywhere.  Our whole family had left
नहीं जाते। पूरी फैमिली हमारी निकल गई थी
together.  We went sitting on top of each other.
एक साथ ही। हम एक दूसरे के ऊपर बैठकर गए
This is Sajjad who
थे। यह है सज्जाद जो अपनी फैमिली को लेकर
fled to Safely with his family but when he returned he saw that the
सेफली भागे पर लौट कर देखा कि उनका मेहनत
house he had built with hard work had collapsed.  So this
से खड़ा किया घर ढेर हो चुका था। तो ये
house is completely damaged.
वाला घर पूरा का पूरा डैमेज हो गया
This kitchen was what was left.  His
है। जो ये वाला किचन बचा हुआ था। उसका
door has been torn from here.  And because of the
दरवाजा यहां से फट गया है। और उसकी आवाज
pressure exerted by his voice, this window has also been destroyed.
से जो प्रेशर पड़ा उससे ये विंडो भी खत्म
This is the main door outside.  The shelling is
यह मेन दरवाजा है बाहर का। यहां पे शेलिंग
here and went out from here.  If there
यहां पे पड़ी है और यहां से बाहर गई। अगर
were any humans here, Allah should have saved
कोई इंसान होते यहां अल्लाह ने बचाना था
them.   There has
इनको।
n't been so much swelling before.  We
इससे पहले इतनी स्वेलिंग नहीं हुई। हमने
called SAO sir and told him that we needed a car.   Let
एसएओ साहब को कॉल की कि हमें गाड़ी चाहिए।
us get out of here.  S SAO sir said
हमें यहां से निकल। एस एसएओ साहब ने बोला
now wait for 10-20 minutes.  The car will reach you.
अब 10 20 मिनट रुको। गाड़ी आप तक पहुंच
Now I have to go out again.  But we were so
जाएगी। अब फिर निकलना है। लेकिन हमें इतना
scared, so terrified.  For that reason, we
डर था, इतना खौफ था। उस वजह से हम उससे
left before him with our car.  Neither
पहले ही निकल गए अपनी गाड़ी करके। ना
clothes are left nor anything is left.  Our entire house
कपड़े रहे, ना कुछ रहा है। पूरा मकान
became a demolition.  At present, we
हमारा डमेश हो गया। इस वक्त हम कई जगह पर
live on rent in many places.  It is difficult to even imagine that
किराए पे रहते हैं। सोचना भी मुश्किल है
scene when one's own room becomes a corner of death.  It
वो मंजर जब अपना ही कमरा मौत का कोना बन
takes years to nurture the home.  But it
जाए। सालों लगते हैं घर को सींचने में। पर
only takes one night to destroy everything.   There
बस एक रात चाहिए सब तबाह करने के लिए।
was a lot of loss.  We haven't even taken out any stuff yet.  The
बहुत नुकसान हुआ। अभी हमने कुछ सामान भी
children's bags are inside
नहीं निकाला। बच्चों के बेग अंदर रहे हैं
and we don't even have books and clothes to put inside.  It's
और किताबें कपड़े लगाने के लिए भी हमें
completely finished from top to bottom.
नहीं है। ऊपर से ले नीचे तक ही पूरे खत्म।
While drills were going on across the country, this
जहां पूरे देश में ड्रिल्स चल रही थी इस
city did not even receive any warning.   He
शहर को कोई वार्निंग भी नसीब नहीं हुई।
just told us that there will be a blackout.   Switch
सिर्फ हमें बोला था ब्लैक आउट हो जाएगा।
off the lights completely.  If it is fair
बत्तियां शतियां बंद कर देना। अगर फेयर
then don't leave from where you come.   I was
होता है तो जहां आओ वहीं से निकलना नहीं।
asleep at night.  First, there was an explosion.
रात के टाइम सोए थे। पहले एक धमाका हुआ।
Then another one happened.  Then my son called me.  He
फिर दूसरा हुआ। फिर मुझे बेटे ने फोन
said, Papa, there are explosions happening.  So
किया। बोला पापा धमाके हो रहे हैं। तो
I told him to go to sleep, there is no such issue right now.
मैंने बोला उसको तू सो जा अभी ऐसी कुछ बात
So when more shelling started happening,
नहीं है। तो जब ज्यादा शेलिंग होने लगी तो
I kept some of the children and family
फिर मैंने बच्चे फैमिली कोई सीढ़ियों के
under the stairs and took some to the back room.
नीचे रख दिया कुछ पीछे वाले कमरे में लेकर
Odoo has helped us to bring this video to you.  Odoo is a business
हमारी मदद की है ओडू ने। ओडu एक बिज़नेस
platform with 45 plus apps to
प्लेटफार्म है जिसके 45 प्लस एप्स बिनेसेस
make businesses successful at a very reasonable
को सक्सेसफुल बनाते हैं एट अ वेरी रीज़नेबल
price.  And now Odoo is bringing India's
प्राइस। और अब ओडू ला रहा है इंडियास
Biggest Tech Business Event on 13th and 14th
बिगेस्ट टेक बिजनेस इवेंट 13th और 14th
August.  Here you
अगस्त को। यहां आप रनाउंड इन्फ्लुएंसर्स,
can learn from runaround influencers, experts, and the Odoo team.
एक्सपर्ट्स और ओडू की टीम से सीख सकते
Ultimate Tech Experience, Business
हैं। अल्टीमेट टेक एक्सपीरियंस, बिजनेस
Networking and Unlimited Fun.  Its entry
नेटवर्किंग और अनलिमिटेड फन। इसकी एंट्री
is absolutely free.  There will be 150 talks and live demos
एकदम फ्री है। 150 टॉक्स और लाइव डेमोस
that will help every business owner.   There will be
होंगे जो हर बिजनेस ओनर को हेल्प करेंगे।
over 20,000 attendees, 200 plus
20,000 से ज्यादा अटेंडस होंगे, 200 प्लस
booths.  There will be an opportunity to learn from real business owners from every field
बूथ्स होंगे। हर फील्ड के रियल बिज़नेस ओनर
and there will also be a concert and
से सीखने का मौका मिलेगा और कॉन्सर्ट और
after party and this will take place
आफ्टर पार्टी भी होगी और यह होगा महात्मा
at Mahatma Mandir, Gandhinagar.  So what are you
मंदिर गांधीनगर में। सो व्हाट आर यू
waiting for?  Register from the link
वेटिंग फॉर? रजिस्टर करो फ्रॉम द लिंक
below.  There is no banker in this village.  At present no
बिलो। इस गांव में कोई बैंकर नहीं। फिलहाल
one has a banker in the entire Udi.  The
तो पूरी उडी में बैंकर किसी के पास नहीं
entire Udi has been destroyed.  You can see the
है। पूरी उडी तबाह हो गई है। आप देख सकते
loss; you can see for yourself
हो नुकसान का तो आप खुद ही देख सकते हो
how much loss has occurred.  We have
कितना नुकसान हुआ है। उरी को हमने न्यूज़
seen Uri a lot in news and movies.  But have you
में मूवीज में बहुत देखा है। पर क्या उरी
ever heard of the people of Uri?  It is
के लोगों को कभी सुना है? हर बॉर्डर विलेज
necessary to have bunkers in every border village.  If there were no bunkers, the
में बंकर्स होना जरूरी है। अगर बंकर नहीं
house itself would become a battle field
होते तो घर ही एक बैटल फील्ड बन जाता है
and the entire city would be a picture of destruction.
और पूरा शहर तबाही की तस्वीर।
Banker is very important and along with him there should be
बैंकर तो बहुत जरूरी है और उसके साथ-साथ
some relief also so that he
कुछ रिलीफ भी होना चाहिए ताकि इसको कुछ कर
can do something.  Let us come and live here again.  The firing
सके। हम दोबारा इसमें आकर बसें। फायरिंग
started and we were all in the car.  So when the
स्टार्ट हुई और हम सब गड़ी में थे। तो जब
shuffling became too much, we saw that this
ज्यादा शलिंग हो गई तो हमने देखा कि ये
house was going to be demolished.  So we ran away from here.   After getting
मकान जाने वाला है। तो हम यहां से भाग गए।
out from here with great difficulty after hiding, there is another small house.  We
निकले तो एक और मकान है छोटा सा। उसमें हम
sat in it.  On top of that, the shelling that happened
बैठ गए। उस पर भी वो गोलाबारी जो हुआ वो
also caused damage.  We sat like this the whole night.
हुआ उसका भी नुकसान। पूरी रात बैठे रहे हम
A war changes the lives of many people.   Of
एक वॉर कई लोगों की जिंदगी बदल देती है।
those brave soldiers who risk their lives
उन ब्रेव सोल्जर्स की जो अपनी जान की बाजी
so that we can continue to live in this country.
लगाते हैं ताकि हम रह रहे ये देश रहे।
I am very proud.  My father was martyred.
मुझे बहुत गर्व है। मेरे बाबा शहीद हुए।
But also of those families who do
पर उन परिवारों की भी जिनको इस जंग के बीच
n't even get a chance to save their lives amidst this war.  We would have
अपनी जान बचाने का मौका तक नहीं मिलता। हम
cast our votes, we would have voted for everyone.  He used to
वोट्स डालते हर किसी को वोट डालते। वो
promise us that we will
हमारे से प्रॉमिस करते कि हम आवाम के लिए
do everything for the people.  So if he had to do
सब कुछ करेंगे। तो उन्होंने अगर उनको यह
all this.  You should have alerted us first.   By
सब कुछ करना था। पहले हमें अलर्ट तो करते।
killing us people in this manner, by
हम पीपल्स को इस तरीके से मारकर, अपने
destroying our parents, we lost even our shadow.  At
मां-बाप को उजाड़ कर हमारा साया भी चला
this time, during the country's major wars, the
गया। इस टाइम देश की बड़ी जंगों में सीमा
small border villages travel the most.
के छोटे विलेजेस सबसे ज्यादा सफर करते
This country expands like this.  Even today children are scared.
हैं। ये देश ऐसा फैलता है। आज भी बच्चे डर
Not living in homes.  Whenever there is a
रहे हैं। घरों में नहीं रह रहे। जैसी
task or a dish is rung, the
टास्क कोई होता है या कोई सालन बजती है तो
kids hide.  Tell me what
बच्चे छुपते हैं। बोलते हैं आप क्या
will you do?  There should be peace here too.  There
करेंगे? यहां से भी अमन होना चाहिए। वहां
should be peace there too.  They are dying.  They are dying.  The
से भी अमन होना चाहिए। मर रहे हैं। मर रहे
poor man is dying.  The poor will die from there too.
हैं। गरीब मर रहा है। वहां से भी गरीब
Poor people are dying here also.   It is the
मरेंगे। यहां से भी गरीब मर रहे हैं।
common people who are travelling mostly in this.  If, for
इसमें ज्यादा सफर आवाम ही कर रही है। अगर
example, they have to fight.  We are not
मिसाल के तौर इनको जंग करनी है। हम नहीं
saying don't fight.  But first
बोल रहे हैं मत करो जंग। मगर पहले जो आवाम
save the people.  There were big gifts.   I was
है उसको तो बचाओ। बड़ी-बड़ी तोहफे थी।
very scared of them.  The children got scared and started crying.
इनसे बहुत डर लगा। बच्चे डर गए रोने लगे।
We all ran away from here.  Look, this war
हम इधर से भाग गए सब। देखो जी ये जंग जो
should not happen.  Yes.  People are facing a lot of
है ये नहीं होना चाहिए। जी। इसमें बहुत
loss due to this.  People are not able to sleep.
नुकसान है लोगों का। नींद नहीं आ रही
This is because of this fear.
लोगों के। ये डर सी डर की वजह से। इस वक्त
All the people here right now are in fear.  This was the
जो लोग हैं ये सब खौफ में हैं। यही तो
time when the country's attention
टाइम था जब देश की नजरें नेशनल मीडिया की
turned towards the national media.  But the national media
तरफ बढ़ी। पर नेशनल मीडिया ने तो फेक
ran fake alert news.  There has been
अलर्ट न्यूज़ चलाई। लाहौर और इस्लामाबाद
huge devastation in Lahore and Islamabad.  An innocent person was
में बहुत बड़ी तबाही हुई है। एक बेगुनाह
declared a terrorist.  After Operation Sindoor,
को टेररिस्ट बता दिया। ऑपरेशन सिंदूर के
information is now being received about terrorist Mohammad
बाद अब जानकारी मिल रही है आतंकी मोहम्मद
Iqbal also.  A panic was spread by repeatedly sounding war sirens
इकबाल की भी। एक दहशत फैलाई वॉर साइरेंस
and even
बार-बार बचा के और यहां तक कि गेम्स की
calling the games videos as war videos.
वीडियो को वॉर वीडियो बोल दिया।
What do I think of this nonsense
इस बेवकूफी के बारे में मैं क्या सोचती
?  Whose hatred increased so much when the war stopped
हूं? जिसकी नफरत वॉर रुकने पर इतनी ज्यादा
that he started abusing our own country's Foreign
बढ़ गई कि हमारे ही देश के फॉरेन
Secretary.  When the
सेक्रेटरी को गालियां देना शुरू कर दी। जब
enemy country was trying to break our unity.
दुश्मन देश हमारी एकता तोड़ने की कोशिश कर
When the army was fighting them,
रहा था। जब आर्मी उससे लड़ रही थी, फिर भी
why was our national media still supporting that country?
क्यों हमारा नेशनल मीडिया उस देश का साथ
I have a passionate love for
दे रहा था। मुझे एक जुनूनी मोहब्बत है
our country.  That's why I maintain my aim to
हमारे देश से। इसलिए मैं यह ऐ रखती हूं कि
bring to you stories from every district of India in a genuine and honest manner.  So will you
पहुंचाऊं एक एमथी और सच्चाई के साथ। तो
tell me what is special in your district?
बताओगे मुझे क्या खास है आपके जिले में?